Inventory of the James Barron Hope Papers (II) 1820-1923
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
James Barron Hope Papers (II), 1820-1923.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 93 H77
195 items.
Correspondence and literary works, chiefly 1861-1874, of James Barron Hope (1829-1887), who was a soldier, author and newspaper editor, of Norfolk and Williamsburg, Virginia.
Benjamin Stoddert Ewell,; John Goode,; William Mahone,; Hugh Blair Grigsby,; John Lesslie Hall,; John Blair Hoge,; Annie Beverley Whiting Hope,; James Barron Hope,; Jane Armistead Barron Hope,; Bradley Tyler Johnson,; Jonathan Pembroke Jones,; John Bankhead Magruder,; John Tyler,; William Freeman Vilas,; Robert Charles Winthrop.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 195 items, 1961.
Biographical/Historical Information
James Barron Hope was born 23 March 1829 in Norfolk, Virginia. He was the grandson of Commodore James Barron (1769-1851) and son of Wilton Hope and Jane Armistead (Barron) Hope (1791-1862). James Barron Hope graduated from the College of William and Mary. He practiced law and was the commonwealth's attorney for Norfolk. He married Annie Beverley Whiting (1825-1920) in 1857. The couple had two daughters, Jane ("Janey" or "Jennie") Barron Hope (b. 1859?) and Ann ("Nanny") Hope. James Barron Hope is known primarily for his poetry, serving as the official poet of the 250th anniversary of the Jamestown settlement. He published several volumes of writings and also edited newspapers. Hope died in 1887.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence and literary works, chiefly 1861-1874, of James Barron Hope (1829-1887), soldier, author (poet, orator, and novelist), and newspaper editor, of Norfolk and Williamsburg, Virginia. The papers deal mainly with his 1849 duel with Jonathan Pembroke Jones; his West Indies naval cruise (1851-1852); his Confederate military service (1861-1865); and the aborted 1874 William Mahone-Bradley Johnson duel, in which Hope was Mahone's second.
The majority of correspondence with his family is with his wife Annie Beverley (Whiting) Hope, and his mother, Jane Armistead (Barron) Hope. Prominent correspondents include Benjamin S. Ewell, John Goode, Hugh Blair Grigsby, John Lesslie Hall, John Blair Hodge, General Bradley T. Johnson, General John B. Magruder, President John Tyler, William F. Vilas, and Robert C. Winthrop. The collection also contains numerous newspaper clippings.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 3 Series. Series 1 contains personal correspondence; Series 2 contains the writings of James Barron Hope; Series 3 contains miscellaneous material.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject and then chronologically by date.
Additional Related, Separated and Bibliographic Material
Bibliography
The following four bibliographic references are books that contain poems and stories written by James Barron Hope and located within Swem Library, College of William and Mary. See the College of William and Mary, Swem Library's online catalogue for other published works.
Hope, James Barron. A Collection Of Poems.Richmond: A. Morris, 1859.
Call Number: PS1999 .H4 1859
Hope, James Barron. Leon di Monota: And Other Poems.Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott & Co., 1857.
Call Number: PS1999 .H4 L3
Hope, James Barron. Under The Empire; Or, The Story Of Madelon.Norfolk: J. B. Hope & Co., 1878.
Call Number: PS1999 .H4 U5
Hope, James Barron. A Wreath of Virginia Bay Leaves.Richmond: West, Johnston & Co., 1895.
Call Number: PS1999 .H4 W7
Newspapers
The following two bibliographic references refer to daily newspapers that were edited by James Barron Hope and are located within Swem Library, College of William and Mary. The newspapers are both available on microfilm.
Hope, James Barron, ed. The Norfolk Landmark.(Daily Newspaper) Norfolk: James Barron Hope & Co., 1873-1887.
Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Call Number: AN47 .N67 N492
Hope, James Barron, ed. The Norfolk Virginian.(Daily Newspaper) Norfolk: G.A. Sykes & Co., 1865-1874.
Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Call Number: AN47 .N67 N678
Articles
The following two articles can be found in the magazine the Virginia Cavalcade, Swem Library Stacks, College of William and Mary. Call Number: F221. V8
Simms, Lyman Moody. James Barron Hope, Virginia's Laureate. In Virginia Cavalcade. Vol. 19, No. 3 (1970), pages 22-29
Wermuth, Paul Charles. An Ode to Reconciliation. In Virginia Cavalcade. Vol. 7, No. 2 (1957), pages 14- 17.
Related Material
There are two collections within the Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary that relate to this Collection. They include the Samuel Barron Papers and the James Barron Papers.
The Samuel Barron Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary; include papers and correspondence of three generations of Samuel Barrons, all of whom were involved in naval affairs. Samuel Barron Papers, 1793-1942.538 items.Collection number: Mss. 65 B29
The James Barron Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary; include correspondence and papers of Commodore James Barron relating to his career in the United States Navy, and especially relating to the Chesapeake-Leopard Affair in 1807 and to his duel with Stephen Decatur. James Barron Papers, 1776-1899.2,759 items.Collection number: Mss. 65 B27
Separated Material
The James Barron Hope Papers (I), Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. James Barron Hope Papers (I), 1835-1907.993 items.Collection number: Mss. 65 H77
Materials include correspondence, manuscript poems, editorials, stories, and sketches.
Index Terms
Persons:
Ewell, Benjamin Stoddert, 1810- 1894.; Goode, John, 1829-1909.; Mahone, William, 1826-1895.; Grigsby, Hugh Blair, 1806- 1881.; Hall, J. Lesslie (John Lesslie), 1856-; Hoge, John Blair, 1825-1896.; Hope, Annie Beverley Whiting, 1825-1920.; J. B. H. (James Barron Hope), 1829-1887.; Hope, Jane Armistead Barron, 1791- 1862.; Johnson, Bradley Tyler, 1829-1903.; Jones, Jonathan Pembroke.; Magruder, John Bankhead, 1807-1871.; Tyler, John, 1790- 1862.; Vilas, William F. (William Freeman), 1840-1908.; Winthrop, Robert C. (Robert Charles), 1809- 1894.
Subjects:
American poetry--19th century.; Dueling- -Virginia.; Yorktown (Va.)--History--Siege, 1781--Centennial celebrations, etc.
Occupations:
Poets, American--19th century-- Correspondence.
Components List
  Series 1: Personal Correspondence
- Personal Correspondence, 1842-1920. (Box-folder 1:1-7)
  - Sam[ue]l Jones, Phil[adelphia, Pennsylvania], to Commodore [James] Barron, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 14 December [18]42., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Bill is enclosed for the school quarter which Barron's grandson [James Barron Hope] began but did not finish before returning to Virginia; regrets that he could not keep [James Barron Hope] to teach him more.
  - Jon[athan] P. Jones, Annapolis, [Maryland], to James [Barron] Hope, [Hampton, Virginia?], 25 March [18]48., 2 pages. Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Don't be astonished by this correspondence; is writing due to the "underground" insult [James Barron Hope] made against his brother almost a year ago; asks where he may be found during the next month so that he may be at his "brother's right hand in this"; peace is desirable between men of sense, and this may be the end result if [James Barron Hope] resolves it correctly; hopes that James Barron Hope will properly understand and answer this letter.
  - [James Barron Hope], [Hampton, Virginia?], to [J. Pembroke Jones], [Annapolis, Maryland?], [post 25 March 1848 - ante 30 March 1849]., 1 page. AL. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Received his communication while at W[illia]m and Mary; calls his attention to an expression implying that a charge by him [James Barron Hope] about his [J. Pembroke Jones] brother was false; asks that the meaning of this charge be explained, if it was meant to be offensive.
  - J. Pembroke Jones, "Pembroke", to J[ames] Barron Hope, Hampton, [Virginia], 30 March 1849., 1 page. Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Does not think he can clarify the passage in question from his previous letter; the spirit in which it was written may be judged from the "general tenor" of the letter; Mr. Jones[?] will leave Hampton on Saturday, to be absent about one week.
  - J[ames] Barron Hope, Hampton, [Virginia], to J. Pembroke Jones, "Pembroke", 9 April 1849., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    His [J. Pembroke Jones] reply to his [James Barron Hope's] last letter "was neither intelligible, or satisfactory;" asks again for an explanation; requests copies of their previous correspondence.
  - J[ames] Barron Hope, Hampt[on, Virginia], to J[onathan] P. Jones,"Pembroke", 21 April 1849., 1 page. Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    [J. Pembroke Jones] reply implies that he is untruthful; his [James Barron Hope's] prior tone and manner were courteous, and not unfeeling as he [J. Pembroke Jones] implied; his friend [Tom] Jones is fully authorized to set up the preliminaries of the meeting that he [James Barron Hope] now demands.
  - J. Pembroke Jones, ["Pembroke"?], to J[ames] Barron Hope, Hampton, [Virginia], 24 April 1849., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    In response to his last note, he [J. Pembroke Jones] agrees to [James Barron Hope's] proposition; His friend J. L[imkins] Jones will arrange all the preliminaries for the meeting.
  - J. Pembroke Jones, ["Pembroke"], to Tho[ma]s R. Jones, Hampton, Virginia, 24 April [18]49., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    In the absence of his friend he proposes to meet [James Barron] Hope on Thursday morning, if possible; in order to avoid problems from the civil authorities, he requests that he [Thomas R. Jones] meet his friend [J. Limkins Jones] tomorrow to make further arrangements.
  - J[ames] B[arron] Hope,[Hampton, Virginia?], to Jno P[embroke] Jones, ["Pembroke"?], 24 April 1849., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Tenders an apology for his note of this morning, which was offensive in tone; the note was written under excitement, as he feared arrest; his [J. Pembroke Jones] reasons for postponing their meeting are sufficient; suggests that they meet at the earliest time possible; warns of possible interference.
  - [J. Pembroke Jones, n.p., to James Barron Hope, n.p.], [post 24 April 1849 - ante July 1849]., 1 page. Fragment of AN. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Opening part of correspondence written by [J. Pembroke Jones]; he has temporarily left town; suspecting [James Barron Hope] of acting dishonestly.
  - Jno. Limkins Jones, Old Point, [Virginia], to Thomas Jones, C[harles City County, Virginia],25 April 1849., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    The difficulty which prevented the earlier meeting of their friends has been removed; is now ready to confer and make necessary arrangements for a meeting.
    Including ALS from T[homas] S. J[ones],[Old Point, Virginia], to [James Barron Hope], [Hampton, Virginia?]; he received the enclosed note and hastened to have it read by [James Barron Hope]; suggests that a reply be sent under envelope to him. 1 page.
  - J. Pembroke Jones, ["Pembroke"?]. to J[ames] Barron Hope, Hampton, [Virginia], 21 May 1849., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Did not mean to question his [James Barron Hope] veracity; he had no intentions of taunting [James Barron Hope], but was instead referring to his own behavior, when they talked in Williamsburg; however, if his feeling that his brother is in the right is taken as offensive enough for the challenge to stand, he accedes to it; his friend Mr. J. [Limkins] Jones will arrange things; wishes that he would have received his [James Barron Hope] note before their conversation; hopes that the misunderstanding is removed.
    Includes AN by [James Barron Hope], sketching a reply to [J. Pembroke Jones]; conveys understanding for his stance. 1 page.
  - Jno. Limkins Jones, n.p., to Tho[ma]s F. Jones, n.p., [post 21 May 1849]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Terms to be observed during the [Hope-Jones] duel.
  - James [Barron Hope], Norfolk, [Virginia], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], n.p., 28 February 1851., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Encloses cheque for $50; considers Papa's [James Barron] health to be excellent.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], n.p., [post 23 March 1851 - ante 23 March 1852]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    His ship's neat and warlike appearance; Port-au-Prince, and "the peculiarities of these Negro Legislators, & their country"; encounters a funeral; dismisses the "free and easy, devil-may-care habits of these places"; wants her to write him at his next destination, Pensacola, [Flordia]; a dispatch just arrived informing the crew that "the Commodore [?]" is in a nearby town; details his efforts to become a good and moral man.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Hampton, Virginia], [ante 21 April 1851]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Enjoyable companionship with Papa [James Barron] the previous Saturday he went with Uncle Sam[uel Barron] on board the Pennsylvania; his enjoyment of the band which played and some pleasant new acquaintances; attended church with Uncle Samuel but was disappointed by the theatrical minister; claims to have " fattened very perceptably;" relays the love of family members; requests that she send word to Annie Whiting that he will write her by Monday's mail.
  - James [Barron Hope], La Guyra, Venezuela, to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], n.p., [post 21 April 1851 - ante 23 March 1852]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    The ship's dangerous voyage; the extremely tall Andes mountains; in such beautiful scenery, where God's majesty is so apparent, it is hard to believe that the inhabitants could be "less than Christians;" given a tour of a town by an American resident; their party surprises Spanish girls while bathing; will visit Caracas next; affection for her.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Hampton, Virginia?], [post 21 April 1851 - ante 13 November 1851]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    His visit to and first view of Caracas; marvels at the beauty of Caracas, with its red roofs and pale green river; encountered the "wretched" looking Venezuelan army soldiers; put in a very dirty hotel room, which he had cleaned; accompanied an American gentleman late at night to see the sights; toured the capitol building, but wasn't impressed; expressions of love.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina], 29 July [1851?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    His good health; gets along well with the Flag-officer, who is a charitable man; he [James Barron Hope] writes many dispatches; attended church yesterday; sends his love.
    Includes ALS from James [Barron Hope], Navy Yard, [Norfolk, Virginia?], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina]. Asks if she received her brandy and small notes; take care of herself and the children; write soon.
  - James [Barron Hope], Pensacola, Florida, to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Hampton, Virginia], 13 November 1851., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Joy at being in a place where mail can be easily received; worries about not hearing form his mother recently; his uncle is away on a hunting exhibition; walked by the Commodore, who surprisingly recognized him and invited him to dinner; attended church; enjoyed meeting several "pretty and agreeable girls" that night; asks her to write, and have his friends send him newspapers (The Hampton Enterprise).
  - James [Barron Hope], Pensacola, Florida, to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Hampton, Virginia?], 24 November 1851., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Concern over his letters not arriving; received a fine letter from "Grand Ma"; numerous expressions of affection and devotion; Uncle Pender[grast] returned from his hunting trip and gave him a cordial greeting; he spends many evenings with him and the Commodore; he is growing "uncomfortably fat," and his ship mates and lady friends say his is becoming quite handsome.
  - James [Barron Hope], Pensacola, [Florida], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Hampton, Virginia?], 18 December 1851., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Explanation of the whereabouts of a missing letter; description of the extremely cold weather; the beauty of the ship when ice-covered; concern for her health during the cold weather in Virginia; uncertain of when his ship will depart.
  - James [Barron Hope], Pensacola, [Florida], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Hampton, Virginia?], 30 December 1851., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Wishes her a happy New Year with love; many thanks for her love and wisdom; promises to write often during his voyage to the Mediterranean, and wants many letters in return.
  - James [Barron Hope],[Pensacola, Florida], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Hampton, Virginia], 30 January 1852., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    His voyage to the Mediterranean has begun with beautiful weather, especially for January; assures her of the ship's safety; his cruise will visit the W[est] I[ndies] Isl[an]ds; he will not forget her or her precepts.
  - James [Barron Hope], standing out to sea [Pensacola, Florida], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], 30 January 1852., 2 pages. (Box-folder 1:2)
    His ship's departure briefly delayed; received letters from both his mother and their friend Miss Lizzie [?]; feelings of love for her; he is in " excellent health;" he met Peter Massenburg, who works in the yard.
  - James [Barron Hope],[Pensacola, Florida?], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Hampton, Virginia], 6 June [18]52., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    His ship has received orders to depart tomorrow; tells her to look for his ship ten days after receiving this letter.
  - Jane A. [(Barron)] Hope, Hampton, [Virginia], to [Miss J. C. Applewhart], [Flavanna County, Virginia], 17 July 1852., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    She [Miss Applewhart] is much missed while away visiting relatives; James' return on the Cyane and what a blessing it is; the imminent court-martial of the Cyane's Captain Pain; her great affection for her friend; thanks God for James' safe return.
  - James [Barron Hope],[Portsmouth, Virginia?], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Hampton, Virginia], 6 August 1852., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Worries about lack of mail, but cannot leave to investigate, as he has to testify in a court case; will visit in a few days; has not visited Norfolk in some time, due to her departure from it and the small number of friends there; has been on board for a large portion of the time; his health is fine.
  - James Barron Hope, [Hampton, Virginia?], to [Caroline M. Campbell], [Baltimore, Maryland], 22 January 1857., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Paraphrases a famous conversation illustrating the inability of an author to self-criticize; thanks her for her candid comments, which improve his works.
  - James [Barron Hope], Eastville, Virginia, to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], n.p., 18 April 1858., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    His first note to her blew into the sea; pleasant voyage across the bay; found his friend Dr. Bob, who treated him kindly; dined today at Mr. Fisher's house, which is close to the ocean, and is within "pistol shot" of a burial place of the Gingaskin Indian tribe; asks her in jest to make a huge bag so he can tote her around with him; terms of endearment.
    Including ALS from James [Barron Hope], Eastville, Virginia, to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], n.p.; visited [Chiru's?] grave, and reminds himself to subjugate the uncharitable feelings which sometimes rise up in his heart; will recite his poem at 11 o'clock tomorrow. 1 page.
  - James [Hope Barron], Hampton, Virginia, to Carrie [Campbell], [Baltimore, Maryland], 29 May 1858., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Regrets not having corresponded in so long; his utter happiness since his marriage on June 10, 1857; how well-received his sketches, essays, and criticisms to the newspaper have been; example of how one lady compared him to Edgar Allan Poe; wants frank criticism of his works from her; his family's sympathy for her family's recent distress; Manna [Jane A. (Barron) Hope] and Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope] send their love.
  - John Tyler, "Sherwood Forest" [Charles City County, Virginia], to J[a]mes Barron Hope, [Hampton, Virginia], [10] January 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    His friends have been pressuring him to publish his "views on the present great crisis;" he is sending them to Richmond without sending them to him [James Barron Hope] first, due to a lack of time; they should be printed in Richmond's Wednesday papers; hopes that they meet his approval; asks for his criticism of them.
  - W[illia]m A. Moncure, Richmond, Virginia, to James Barron Hope, Hampton, [Virginia], 16 January 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Response to his inquiry concerning Virginia state stocks; quote of stock amount needed to realize $1000; as the stock is in his mother's name [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], he would need the power of attorney from her to execute a transaction; encloses a power of attorney form.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope], n.p., [ca. 1 May 1861]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    From Fay Jones' desk in the Tannery Bank; mentions purchases made for family. General Johnston is in Richmond "at last."
  - Mary [Blake], New York, [New York], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?], 18 May [1861?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Hopes that letter will be delivered, despite the "dreadful state...throughout our once united and happy land."; glad to receive Janes's last letter, with its postscript from James; visited C[a]pt[ain] and Mrs. [David G.] Farragut in Hastings, [New York]; Frank [Mary's son?] is on duty at the Charleston, [South Carolina] Navy Yard, and wants to marry Sallie [?], but "this surely is no time for adding to one's loved [ones] and responsibilities."; her love to family and friends.
  - James [Barron Hope], Richmond, [Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope], n.p., 5 June 1861., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Safe arrival in Richmond; has thought over their affairs; has been informed tht the "outrages at Hampton have been much exaggerated - Segar is hand and glove with the invaders;" [Jefferson] "Davis' arrival has opperated like a spell;" 50,000 men reported to be ordered from the South, it is hoped that the country will be cleared before long; he shall be careful; love to his family.
    Includes ALS from James [Barron Hope], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], n.p., stressing his good health. 1 page.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], [post 5 June 1861 - ante 3 February 1862]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Will write her a long letter tomorrow; Clay [?] is very well, and in W[illiam]sburg, [Virginia]; asks if his mother has changed her draft [?].
  - James [Barron Hope],[Richmond, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?], [post 5 June 1861 - ante 11 April 1865]., 4 pages. Incomplete. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Dined and talked with his friend Thompson [?]; borrowed two volumes of Clarissa Harlowe from the state library; assures her that he is comfortable; don't worry about the news; Lee's army is daily gaining strength; resolution of building a new home; asks for an 8 page letter; does she like the book he sent?; how very much he loves her.
  - James [Barron Hope], Richmond, [Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope], n.p., 10 June 1861., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)